Martin Green Papers MS085
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Martin Green Papers
1960 -- 2003
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Green, Martin
MS085
8.4 Linear Feet 7 boxes
2 Digital Object(s)
Arrangement
Organized in two series: Manuscript drafts and Unprocessed accessions.
Custodial History
The materials were donated to the archive in Spring 2003. Additional accessions were made in 2010 and 2011.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains drafts of several Martin Green manuscripts, handwritten notes on both loose paper and in notebooks, and research material in English, French, Russian, and German. There are also subject files which include correspondence and book proposals.
Related Materials
MS008 Else von Richthofen collection. Digital Collections and Archives. Medford, MA.
Biographical / Historical
Martin Burgess Green (1927-2010) was a professor in the English Department at Tufts University from 1963-65 and then again from 1968-94. He received a B.A. from St. John's College in Cambridge, where he studied with the legendary F.R. Leavis. Martin received his M.A. from King's College of the University of London in 1951, and then served in the Royal Air Force for two years before teaching in Turkey and France. In 1957 he earned his Ph.D. from the University of Michigan. Professor Green published 37 books on a variety of topics ranging from an examination of Tolstoy and Gandhi to an analysis of the Robinson Crusoe adventure story. He is also known for his work on the Von Richthofen sisters and their involvement with Otto Gross related to the Ascona Movement in Switzerland.
While at Tufts, Professor Green was recognized for his work with two Guggenheim Fellowships, one awarded in 1974 and the other in 1977; a residency at the Woodrow Wilson International Center for Scholars in 1980-1981; and a fellowship from the National Endowment for the Humanities, awarded in 1987.
His published works include: Mirror for Anglo Saxons; Dreams of Adventure, Deeds of Empire; The Great American Adventure; The Robinson Crusoe Story; The Challenge of the Mahatmas; Tolstoy and Gandhi, Men of Peace; The Origins of Nonviolence; The Von Richthofen Sisters; Children of the Sun; and The Triumph of Pierrot.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. This collection may require review before it is available for use. Please contact DCA for further details.
Faculty papers; Green, Martin
- Manuscript drafts, 1960 -- 2003; MS085.001; 3.6 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains fragments and drafts of several Martin Green manuscripts and two book reviews. Subjects include Otto Gross, Tolstoy, Gandhi, the International Fellowship of Reconciliation, and Pacifism.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged alphabetically.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Book reviews, 1987 -- 1988; MS085.001.001.00001 (Box 1)
  - The disappearance of Otto Gross, 1960 -- 2003; MS085.001.001.00002 (Box 1)
  - The empire and dying, 1960 -- 2003; MS085.001.001.00003 (Box 1)
  - [The empire and dying fragment], 1960 -- 2003; MS085.001.001.00004 (Box 1)
  - [International fellowship of reconciliation 1 of 2], 1960 -- 2003; MS085.001.001.00005 (Box 1)
  - [International fellowship of reconciliation 2 of 2], 1960 -- 2003; MS085.001.001.00006 (Box 1)
  - New centers of life, 1960 -- 2003; MS085.001.001.00007 (Box 1)
  - Otto Gross and the varieties of manhood, 1960 -- 2003; MS085.001.001.00008 (Box 1)
  - [Otto Gross and the varieties of manhood fragment 1], 1960 -- 2003; MS085.001.001.00009 (Box 1)
  - [Otto Gross and the varieties of manhood fragment 2], 1960 -- 2003; MS085.001.001.00010 (Box 1)
  - Pacifism, 1960 -- 2003; MS085.001.001.00011 (Box 1)
  - The reception of Hans and Otto Gross in english speaking countries, 1960 -- 2003; MS085.001.001.00012 (Box 1)
  - Saying no to life: Essays on Tolstoy, Gandhi, and world history [1 of 4], 1960 -- 2003; MS085.001.001.00013 (Box 1)
  - Saying no to life: Essays on Tolstoy, Gandhi, and world history [2 of 4], 1960 -- 2003; MS085.001.001.00014 (Box 1)
  - Saying no to life: Essays on Tolstoy, Gandhi, and world history [3 of 4], 1960 -- 2003; MS085.001.001.00015 (Box 1)
  - Saying no to life: Essays on Tolstoy, Gandhi, and world history [4 of 4], 1960 -- 2003; MS085.001.001.00016 (Box 1)
  - [Saying no to life: Essays on Tolstoy, Gandhi, and world history 1 of 4], 1960 -- 2003; MS085.001.001.00017 (Box 1)
  - [Saying no to life: Essays on Tolstoy, Gandhi, and world history 2 of 4], 1960 -- 2003; MS085.001.001.00018 (Box 1)
  - [Saying no to life: Essays on Tolstoy, Gandhi, and world history 3 of 4], 1960 -- 2003; MS085.001.001.00019 (Box 1)
  - [Saying no to life: Essays on Tolstoy, Gandhi, and world history 4 of 4], 1960 -- 2003; MS085.001.001.00020 (Box 1)
  - [Translations of Max Weber letters], 1960 -- 2003; MS085.001.001.00021 (Box 1)
  - [Untitled manuscript fragment 1], 1960 -- 2003; MS085.001.001.00022 (Box 1)
  - [Untitled manuscript fragment 2], 1960 -- 2003; MS085.001.001.00023 (Box 1)
- Additional accessions, 1960 -- 2003; MS085.002; 3.6 Linear Feet
  - Research materials, Subjects files, 1960 -- 2003; MS085-002 (Box 1)
    former barcode 39090015516582g
  - Research materials, MS085-003 (Box 2)
    Includes research materials, books, 3.5" floppy disks (stabilized in DGB), and notebooks. former barcode 39090015516590g
  - Research materials, MS085-004 (Box 3)
    Inventory list in box: Reading and writing journals; some Monte Verita, modernism in literature; misc. essays; Peacemakers/IFOR mss. and materials; Empire: a Life Prospectus and journal. former barcode 39090015516608g
  - Research materials, MS085-005 (Box 4)
    Includes research materials, books, and notebooks. former barcode 39090015516616g
  - Research materials, MS085-006 (Box 5)
    Includes research materials, books, and notebooks. former barcode 39090015516624g
  - Backup 5-23-03, MS085-007
  - Backup 5-23-03, MS085-008
  - Manuscripts and notes, 1960 -- 2003; MS085-009 (Box 6)
    Former barcode 39090011504244g. This box also contains two letters donated by Peter Hirschmann in 2011. No accession number exists for the letters donated by Hirschmann.